What are you doing here?
在这干嘛
oh
哦
I'm sorry.
对不起啊
I scared you.
我吓到你了
It's okay.
没事儿没事儿
What happened to you, Dango?
团子 怎么了你
Xiaoyu
小鱼
What's wrong?
怎么了
I'm in trouble.
我摊上事了
It's alright.
没事啊
Why did you borrow it online?
你干嘛上网上借呀
I have money.
我有钱
Why don't you borrow from me?
你干嘛不管我借啊
Except for Jiebei,
除了借呗
did you use other apps to borrow money?
你没借什么其他的吧
I also used 360 IOU,
还有三六零借条
Xiaomi.
小米
Dango
团子
These are formal loan apps.
这些都是正规借贷
Didn't you borrow
你没借什么
from some unreliable ones?
乱七八糟的吧
There is also a network platform.
还有一个网络平台的
I didn't want to use it actually.
我本来没有想借的
But it says
可是它上面写着
no guarantee or mortgage is required.
无担保 无抵押
The money arrives in one minute.
一分钟到账
I didn't think so much.
我没有想那么多
I used it.
我就借了
Unexpectedly,
没想到
he just came to collect debts.
他刚刚来催债了
Tell me how much money you borrowed.
你告诉我借了多少钱
I borrowed
我 我借了
30,000.
三万
What did you buy?
你买什么了
I didn't buy anything.
我也没买什么
Everything I bought is quite cheap.
就每一样都挺便宜的
Who knows if it adds up...
谁知道加起来就
Are these online loan platforms
这些网络贷
legal?
平台合不合法呀
Can we sue them?
能不能告他们呀
Calm down.
你冷静点
They're not illegal and they don't force you.
人一没违法 二没强迫
How can we sue them?
人怎么告他们呀
It's good that they didn't sue you for overdue.
人没告你逾期就不错了
Dango
团子
When will you pay back the money?
什么时候还钱 赶紧还
Otherwise, the profits will get higher and higher.
要不然利滚利 利滚利
Then you can't pay it back.
就真还不上了
Tomorrow
明天
Xiaoyu, I'm afraid.
小鱼 我害怕
All right.
好了 好了 好了
Don't be afraid.
不怕 不怕
I'm here with you.
有我 有我
It's already like this.
事情已经这样了
Let's pool the money together.
我们先凑一凑啊
You can start now.
你们可以开始了
You go first.
你先吧
God must be punishing me.
一定是老天爷在惩罚我
Don't say that, Dango.
团子 你别这么说
It's you!
找的就是你
In accordance with the Supreme People's Court trial
根据最高人民法院
on issues related to
审理关于民间借贷案件
the application of law
适用法律
in private lending cases,
相关问题的规定
if the annual interest rate exceeds
年利率超过
36%,
百分之三十六的
the exceeding part
超过部分
is invalid.
无效
It means that
意思就是说
they lend usury.
他们放高利贷
The illegal part
不合法的部分
doesn't have to be returned.
团子都不用还
That's right.
没错
According to the agreement signed by Dango and the platform,
根据团子和平台签定的
the annual interest rate is 20%.
百分之二十的年利率
Overdue interest is continuous compound interest.
逾期利息 复利日万五
If we calculate it like this,
这么算下来的话
the money of Dango is
团子的钱是
thirty-five point
百分之三十五点
nine percent.
九
It's short of 0.1%.
差了零点一个点
It doesn't belong to usury and can't be sued.
不是高利贷 告不了
Are they so insidious?
这么阴险吗他们
Can't it be rounded?
就不能四舍五入吗
No.
四舍五入不了
They are just
人家就是专门
fooling little girls like you.
套路像你这种
Whether the appearance
不管是看起来
or psychology
还是骗起来
are easy to be fooled.
都很容易上当的小姑娘
Ah...
哎
You're a sophomore.
你就是个大二的学生
Are you professional enough?
你会不会不是很专业
I am a talented student in law department.
我一法律系高才生
You ask me if I'm professional.
你问我专不专业
Have a look.
你看
Business license, tax registration certificate
营业执照 税务登记证
and organization code and witnesses are shown here.
组织机构代码证人都有
Their qualifications are complete.
资质齐全
On the national credit information
在全国信用信息
publicity platform,
公示平台上
the relevant information can also be found.
也能查到相关信息
In this way,
照这么看来
Dango can't pay less.
团子的钱一分也不能少
She has to pay it back.
都得还
Hello
喂
Are you Mu Xiaoyu?
你是牧小鱼吧
Xiong Zishi has already
熊子时已经
lost contact for several days.
失联好几天了
You tell her to
你通知她
contact me as soon as possible.
抓紧时间联系我
Who are you?
你谁呀
Are you her classmate?
你是她同学吧
She owes me a sum of money.
她欠了我一笔钱
It's overdue for a long time
逾期很久了
but she didn't pay me back.
还是没还我
If she doesn't deal with it,
她要是再不处理的话
we have to take some measures
我们就要采取一些措施
to collect it.
上门去收取了
All right.
好吧
I know.
知 知道了 知道了
Why are they calling
为什么打电话
me?
打到我这儿来了
They ask me to fill in
当时让我填
three emergency contacts,
三个紧急联系人
but I dared not fill in my parents.
我不敢填家里的
I fill in you,
我就填了你的
Hao, and Fanfan.
还有小好姐 还有凡凡
If they come here,
他们要是找过来
then the whole university will know.
那全校就都知道了
At that time,
那到时候
Liu Yanze will know it, too.
刘彦泽也知道了
Xiaoyu, what should I do?
小鱼 我该怎么办呀
Dango
团子
It's not a small number.
这数目不是一个小数目
You should call home.
你还是给家里打电话吧
Call home?
家里
Dango's dad,
团子爸
her dad is not easy to deal with.
团子爸可不太好惹
My dad has been a supermarket security guard
我爸爸做了十三年
for 13 years.
的超市保安
In addition, he usually
加上他平时
likes to watch criminal investigation dramas.
最爱看刑侦剧
There is no thief he can't catch.
没有他抓不住的小偷
There is no theft that he can't solve.
没有他破不了的失窃案
And no one can
更没有人能够
lie in front of him.
在他面前撒谎
People always call him
人送称号
Di Renjie of the department store.
商场百货狄仁杰
So if he knows
所以他要是知道
I've got into such a big trouble,
我闯了这么大的祸
he will...
还不得
Hey,
哎
your dad is so good.
你爸这么厉害
Why are you afraid of usury?
你怕什么高利贷啊
I'm afraid of my dad.
是我怕我爸
And this time I did something wrong.
而且这次是我做错了
Maybe he will
说不定就会把我
kick me out...
扫地出门
At that time,
到时候
I'll be alone.
我孤苦伶仃一个人
I have no money to rent a house.
我没有钱租房子
I can only
我只能
find a man to marry.
随便找个男人嫁了
Then I'll get married without the bride price.
然后结婚没有彩礼不说
My father can't attend my wedding.
我爸爸还不能出席
My mother-in-law will look down on me.
我婆婆多看不起我
Dango
团子
You tell the family.
你跟家里说
It is inevitable to have a fight.
免不了一顿打
But you have to tell your family now.
但你要现在跟家里说
At least you can solve
起码可以解决
the current problem.
当下的问题啊
No way.
绝对不行
I've had my dad
我已经让我爸爸
help me with many things.
帮我摆平够多事了
Now I'm in college.
现在我都大学了
I need to learn to be independent.
要学会独立
I can't ask teachers and parents for help
不能再什么事
in everything.
都告诉老师 告诉家长
Right?
是不是 小鱼
It's only been a few days.
才这么几天
The interest rate has rolled so high.
利息就滚了这么高
I still have some balance in my card.
我卡里还有点余额
Let's pay it back first.
还是给团子先垫上吧
If the interest is
这利息要是
a few hundred yuan, it won't be so difficult.
几百块钱也不难
But except for
主要是她除了这
the cheating loan,
坑爹的借贷之外
she has extra
她外边还有外加
debt of more than 30,000 yuan.
三万多块钱的外债
Even if it is a formal lending platform,
就算是正规的借贷平台
it's not a small amount
照这么利滚利下去
to go on like this.
也不是小数目
Now time is really money.
这下时间真的是金钱了
An extra moment
真的是多一刻
can't even delay.
都不能拖了
Anyway,
不管怎么样
we have to pay off the debts first.
咱们得先把外债还上
How about a part-time job?
要不试试兼职吧
Where I used to work part-time
我之前兼职的地方
is 120 yuan a day.
一天一百二
There are still three thousand a month.
一个月还能有三千呢
It's been too long, Hao.
时间太长了 小好姐
Ah...
哎
Do you remember
你们记不记得
what I told you before,
我之前跟你们说的
the Fast Unloading Application.
那个卸得快应用程序
I have signed up for
我已经报名
the Campus Entrepreneurship Program.
校园创业计划
The teacher said there was a chance.
老师说有戏
When the plan
到时候这个
is handed in,
计划书一交
financing is not a problem.
融资更不是没问题
Don't say 30,000.
别说三万了
300,000 is OK.
三十万都没问题
Are you serious?
你真的假的
When?
什么时候能融上
In a year or a half year or more...
一年半载的吧
I...
我这不
The plan hasn't been handed in yet.
计划书还没交呢嘛
What did I say?
我刚才说什么来着
I knew a junior.
我之前有个学妹
She writes papers on the Internet.
在网上写论文
Stop.
停
Hao
小好姐
That's academic fraud.
学术造假
Don't talk about that.
不瞎说啊
I think she should
我觉得这件事
ask her family for help.
你就得找家里寻求帮助
The more we drag on, the more troublesome it is.
越拖越麻烦
I agree with Nan Bei.
我赞同南北说的
It's right.
道理是这么个道理
But it's impossible for Dango.
团子不可能
Does she have a bad relationship with her parents?
她跟父母关系不好吗
Very good.
非常好
It's just that Dango has been
只是团子从小
naughty and mischievous.
调皮捣蛋的
Her mother has been helping her with the aftermath.
她妈妈一直在帮她善后
And her parents...
然后她爸妈
In order not to let her get into trouble again,
为了不再让她闯祸呢
they are very strict with her.
就管她管得特别紧
Dango always wants to
团子一直想在爸妈面前
establish an independent
树立已经独立
image.
的女性形象
If her parents know about this,
这次这事让她知道了
I don't know what they will do to her.
不知道怎么管她
Dango, drink some water.
团子 喝水
OK.
嗯
I'm sure everyone must have done
我相信大家一定都做了
adequate preparation.
充足的准备
So who can solve
那么今天这个题
today's topic?
谁能破
I can!
我来破
It's really broken.
真的破了
Let's read the topic first.
我们先开题呀
College life...
大学生活
In fact, universal cognition
其实用普适性认知
can solve the question.
就可以了
Then there are self-discipline and heteronomy.
然后是自律和他律
This is a comparative question.
这是一个比较题
I think
我觉得
these two should be
这两个应该是
a relatively large battlefield.
一个比较大的战场
One
一个呢
is the definition of self-discipline and heteronomy.
是自律和他律的定义
Then the more important is criterion.
然后是更重要的判准
Nan Bei, let me add.
南北 我来补充一下
College life is the premise of the topic,
大学生活作为题目前提
combined with the topic stem.
跟题干结合起来的话
The space we discuss
其实我们讨论的空间
is relatively large.
还是比较大的
Because we're in
因为我们处在一个
a special time period.
比较特殊的时间段
Although we are already
虽然我们已经
adults,
是成年人了
we're still in the environment
可是我们还处在
like more than a decade ago.
十几年前
We are familiar with it.
我们比较熟悉的
We are still in the college environment
孩子所处在的
where the children are.
学校的环境当中
This state
这种状态
has an impact on self-discipline and heteronomy.
对自律和他律的影响
It should be what the questioner
应该是出题人
wants us to discuss.
想要我们进行讨论的
Yes.
对
When
我那会儿
I started college,
刚上大学的时候
I just thought
我就想着
I didn't get out of bed for three days and three nights.
三天三夜我都没有下床
At that time, I thought...
当时我就觉得
Eh...
切
You don't go to the bathroom.
你不上厕所
Can you stop interrupting?
能不能别打岔
As a boy, I think
我觉得作为一个男孩
staying up all night, playing games
熬夜通个宵打个游戏
and watching the live broadcast or something
看看直播什么的
are normal.
都很正常
I just feel like
我就觉得
I get out of
好不容易
the control of parents.
脱离了父母的魔爪了
I should enjoy it.
还不得好好自由自由啊
Yes.
是的
When I was a freshman,
我大一的时候
I also want to play everything.
也是什么都想玩
With the girls in my dormitory,
跟宿舍的女生
we practice makeup all night.
练化妆练通宵
I don't expect a girl to
没想到最后有个女生
go to the counter
居然去专柜
as a part-time makeup artist.
兼职当化妆了
I won't say it.
我就不说了
I still can't
我到现在
control my mouth.
还管不住自己的嘴
So
那
does the control of parents belong to heteronomy?
父母的魔掌算不算他律
So the lack of heteronomy
所以说他律的缺失
will result in the loss of self-discipline.
会造成自律的丧失
No.
不对
Heteronomy will cause
他律会造成
binding gap.
约束力的空白
Self-discipline didn't fill in.
自律没有填上
Right.
对
Because we have been
因为我们从小
under control since we were young.
都一直是被管着
There is no
根本就没有什么
self-discipline at all.
自律的能力啊
There is no opportunity for self-discipline.
也没有什么自律的机会
Where is the loss?
何来的丧失呢
I think
我觉得
we don't realize that
我们并没有意识到
no one cares about us now
现在的我们没有人管
means what.
到底意味着什么
Nobody caring
没人管
means that
也就说明
no one will cover for you again.
不会再有人为你兜底
There won't be anyone else
不会再有人
to bear this for you.
为你承担这一切了
Every time
我每次在网上嘻嘻哈哈
I shop online crazily,
剁手的时候
when I see my favorite things
看到自己喜欢的东西
and overspend again and again,
一次次超支的时候
and even when I see the lending platform
甚至是看到借贷平台
and click in,
点进去的时候
I never think too much.
我从来都没有想过太多
I naively thought that
我天真地以为
everything
所有的事情
could be solved.
都是可以解决的
In fact,
事实上
I've been under Dad's protection for too long.
我在爸爸的保护下太久
I don't realize that
根本就没有意识到
the price is so cruel,
这代价这么地残酷
so real,
这么地真实
and so troublesome.
这么地麻烦
So what is our Dango
那我们团子
going to do?
打算怎么办呢
I should face it.
我应该面对它
Hello
喂
dad
爸
I'm in trouble.
我闯祸了
Hey,
哎哎
can you see?
看见没有 看见没有
The man walking towards
那个朝教学楼
the school building
走过来的男人
is Dango's father.
就是团子的爸爸
Dango's father is really cool.
团子爸真有范啊
As for the image of Dango's father,
就团子爸这种形象
if he's not a special soldier,
不当特种兵
he can play gangster movies.
演个警匪片
It will get a score of nine in Douban.
豆瓣评分也得九点几
Am I right?
是吧 团子
Where is Dango?
团子呢
Where does Dango go?
团子去哪儿啦
Oh, my God.
完蛋
Dango runs away.
团子跑了
Are you Xiong Zishi's father?
您是熊爸爸吧
I'm Dango's...
我是团
I'm Zishi's friend.
子时的朋友
She is not in the dormitory.
不在宿舍里
So where did she go?
那她去哪儿了呢
I should have thought of
我早就该想到
her father's deterrent to her.
团子爸对她的威慑力了
Wicked girl
死丫头
She cops out at the last minute.
临阵脱逃
Think about it.
再好好想想
Where the hell can she go?
她到底能去哪儿
It's not the way to escape like this.
这么逃避也不是办法
It seems that
看来只能让
Nan Bei has to hold Dango's dad.
南北拖住团子爸了
Let's go and look for her again.
走吧 再找一找
When will Dango come?
团子什么时候来
She was supposed to be here,
她本来是来找您的
but she was called away by the debate teacher.
但是被辩论老师叫走了
She will be back soon.
应该马上就回了
Really?
真的吗
Yes.
真的
Have you ever heard of a study?
你听说过一个研究吗
When someone tells a lie,
说人在撒谎的时候
his eyeballs
他的眼球
will move to the upper right corner of the eye socket.
会往眼眶的右上角移动
Really?
真 真的吗
Did you realize that
你意识到你的眼球
your eyeballs move?
刚刚动了一下吗
Guess which way it's moving.
你猜是往哪边移动
Uncle, you are so humorous.
叔叔 你真幽默
Where is Dango?
团子在哪儿
She was called away by the teacher.
团子被老师叫走了
This time your eyeballs
这次你的眼球
don't move.
没有动
But
不过
if a person is too anxious,
如果一个人过于焦虑
his hands will unconsciously
他的手会不自觉地
move.
有一些小动作
For example, you.
比如说你
Are you nervous?
你很紧张嘛
What are you worried about?
你在担心着什么
Let me get you a glass of water.
我给您倒杯水去
Sit down.
坐下
You really don't see Dango, right?
你是真没看见团子
I really don't see her.
我真没看见
I'll tell you if I see her.
看见我就告诉你了
The idea of supplementing sugar
补充糖分
is wrong.
这个想法也不对
Where can she go?
她能去哪儿
Where else can she go?
还能去哪儿呢
So stupid.
真笨
Hao, come with me.
小好姐 跟我走
uncle
叔叔
This lamp...
这灯
Gender?
性别
Eh...
性
male
男
Age?
年龄
Nineteen.
十九
Height.
身高
1.78 meters.
一七八
Family status?
家庭状况
I,
我
and my parents.
我爸妈
Three people.
仨人
What is the relationship between you and Dango?
你跟团子什么关系
Ordinary friend.
普通朋友关系
What else?
还有什么关系
We are still debate friends.
我们还有辩友关系
Last night
昨天晚上
Dango called me.
团子给我打电话
She said she got into trouble.
说她自己闯了祸
She says she will tell me what kind of trouble
具体闯的什么祸
when we meet.
她说见面再说
Do you know
你知道
what she does?
她做了什么吗
In other words,
又或者说
what did you do to her?
你对她做了什么
I didn't do anything.
我 我什么都没做
What do you want to do?
你到底想做什么
This...
这个还是
It's better for Dango to tell you.
团子跟你说比较好
So you did.
那就是你做了
I didn't do anything, uncle.
我什么都没做呀 叔叔
Isn't it painful to lie?
撒谎很痛苦吧
Are you suffering?
很煎熬吧
Say it.
说出来
It won't be so painful.
就没那么痛苦了
Uncle, I tell you everything.
叔叔 我全都说
I tell you.
我全都说
Eh...
嗯
When I was in the first grade of primary school,
我小学一年级的时候
I didn't do my math homework once.
我有一次没写数学作业
Because
那是因为
Wang Ergou of the next door
隔壁邻居的王二狗
came to play with me.
来找我玩的时候
Then I forgot to write because I was too tired.
我忘写 玩太累了
But I told the teacher that
但我跟老师说我
Wang Ergou came to me.
王二狗来找我
And I got the wrong homework.
我把作业给拿错了
After I said it,
当时我说出来
I realized how stupid I was.
我才知道自己有多蠢
When Wang Ergou saw me,
王二狗看到我的时候
he exposed me directly.
直接给我揭发了
My mother beat me up.
我妈给我那一顿毒打
In the second grade,
二年级的时候
I lied to Wang Ergou.
我骗王二狗说
I asked him to
你只要把舌头
put his tongue
放在那个
on the frozen water pipe
结了冰的冰水管上
for thirty seconds.
三十秒
And then you
你就可以
could taste the rainbow.
尝到彩虹的滋味
As a result, he
结果他
stuck for thirty minutes.
整整黏了三十分钟
I'm not on purpose.
我真的不是故意的
Teacher
老师
Excuse me.
请问一下熊子时同学
Is Xiong Zishi here or not?
在不在这儿
She came here ten minutes ago.
她十几分钟前来的
She said she was dizzy.
说是头晕
She's resting inside.
在里面休息呢
Oh,
哦
thank you, teacher.
谢谢老师
I told her before.
我之前跟她说过
During military training,
军训的时候
Nan Bei pretended to be sick.
南北装病的事
She looked
她当时就
deeply inspired at the time.
一副深受启发的样子
She's hiding here now.
果然躲这儿来了
OK.
行
Dango
团子
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Am I useless?
我是不是超级没用啊
Your father is as fierce as Lv Bu.
你爸凶得跟吕布似的
I'm afraid, too.
要我 我也害怕
My father will scold me seriously.
我爸肯定会骂死我的
You don't even know
你都不知道
how frugal he is.
他平时有多节省
If he can take a bus,
能坐公交
he won't take a taxi.
就不打车
He never takes a bus if he can walk.
能走路就绝不坐公交
If he knows
他要是知道
I spend money like this,
我这样子乱花钱
he will be furious.
肯定气炸了
Dango
团子
Do you remember
你记不记得
how we
咱们是怎么
became friends?
成为朋友的呀
When I was a child,
小的时候
I always fought with boys.
我总爱跟男生打架
For a long time,
很长一段时间
neither boys nor girls
不管男生还是女生
liked to play with me.
都不爱跟我玩
Only you
就只有你
can eat with me,
陪我一起吃饭
go to school with me,
陪我一起上学
and play with me.
陪我一起玩
You have been like this since you were a child.
你从小就是这样
Like is like.
喜欢就是喜欢
Hate is hate.
讨厌就是讨厌
Do whatever you want to do.
想到什么就去做什么
I actually hope
我其实挺希望
you can always be like this,
你一直都是这个样子
like a little girl who never grows up.
像个长不大的小朋友
But now I think
但是我现在觉得
my idea is quite selfish.
我这个想法挺自私的
I think the college
我觉得学校
creates an illusion for us.
给我们营造一种幻觉
It seems that
好像我们
we are all children.
都是长不大的孩子
We don't need to face society.
还不用去面对社会
We don't have to face the outside world.
不用去直面外面的世界
We forget that
忘记了
in the real world,
在真实的世界里面
no matter what you do,
不论你做什么
you need to bear the consequences
都需要你自己去承担
yourself.
应该承担的后果
Dango
团子
As a friend,
作为朋友
I solemnly tell you.
我郑重地告诉你
Don't evade
不要逃避
the responsibility you should bear.
你应该承担的责任
So
所以
you'd better look up bravely.
要不你勇敢地抬起头
Go to bear the mistakes in front of your father.
去爸爸面前承担错误
Otherwise,
要不然
as your best friend,
作为你闺蜜
I'll force you to come.
我绑也要给你绑去
Because this is my duty
因为这是我做死党
as your best friend.
应尽的责任
When I was a freshman,
大一的时候
I sewed Mengyuan's unwashed socks
我把梦圆没有洗的袜子
into the pillowcase of Dandan.
缝在了蛋蛋的枕套里
He hasn't found out
他一个月都没有找到
where the smell came from for a month.
到底是哪儿来的味
You finally come.
你们可算来了
I'm about to talk about my sophomore year.
我眼看就要说到大二了
I'm sorry, Dad.
对不起啊 爸
I really know that I was wrong this time.
我这次真的知道错了
What's up?
怎么回事啊
I don't know
我也不知道
how I spend so much.
我自己怎么花的
I'm careless.
一个不留神
I'm unconscious.
两个不留神
Then I spend more than I can afford.
就花超了
I used
有
Taobao,
淘宝
JD.com,
京东
and a few Baitiao.
还有几个白条
My classmates have helped me
同学们已经帮我
collect eight thousand yuan.
凑了八千块钱
They help me pay back the internet loan.
让我把网络贷给还了
How much is it altogether?
一共是多少啊
More than 30,000...
三万多
It won't happen again.
不会再有下一次了吧
I won't.
不会
Send me
把银行卡号
your bank card number.
发给我
And
还有
call all your classmates
把你的那些同学们
in
都叫进来
and stop lying down at the door.
别在门口趴着了
It's uncomfortable.
怪难受的
Tell them that
告诉大家
I invite everyone to have a meal.
我请大家一起吃个饭
OK.
好
Thank you, Dad.
谢谢爸
Let's go.
走
Come on.
来
Thank you, uncle.
谢谢叔叔
Thank you for inviting us to have a meal.
谢谢叔叔请我们吃饭
You're welcome.
不客气
Please take care of
我们家团子以后啊
Dango in the future.
拜托你们还要多照顾呢
Then
那
we'll go first.
我们就先走了
I have a competition tomorrow.
我明天还要比赛呢
And I need to train.
还要训练
Eh.
嗯
OK.
好
You can do your business first.
你们先忙
I'll talk with Dango for a while.
我跟团子再聊一会儿
Ah.
啊
Thank you, uncle.
谢谢叔叔
Goodbye.
叔叔再见
See you later.
再见
Dango
团子
Let's sit over there for a while.
咱们去那边坐会儿
OK.
好
Come here.
这儿吧
Ah.
哎
Dad
爸
What?
嗯
This time,
这次
I'm sorry.
对不起啊
Daughter,
闺女
in the future,
以后遇到事
no matter what happens,
无论什么事
you have to tell dad.
都要告诉爸爸
Do you understand?
明白吗
Yes.
嗯
Dad,
爸
does my mom know about this?
我妈她知道我的事了吗
Don't let your mother
这事
know about this.
千万不能让你妈知道
Then where do you get the money?
那你钱哪儿来的啊
This is Dad's private money.
这是老爸的私房钱哪
Cool, dad.
厉害呀 爸
OK.
好
Daughter,
闺女
you prepare well
你好好准备
for tomorrow's competition.
明天的比赛吧
Come on.
先忙去
Okay, then I'm leaving, dad.
行 那我走了 爸
OK.
好
Dad,
爸
thank you.
谢谢爸爸
Bye, dad.
走了 爸
Ah...
哎
It's time to quit smoking.
该戒烟了
After eating together,
我刚吃完饭
I don't think
觉得团子爸
Dango's father is so scary.
也没那么可怕呀
No.
不行啊
I am still scared
我现在看到叔叔
when I see her dad.
还是肝颤
I think it's a pity
我觉得叔叔
that uncle has such a skill
有这么一身本事
as a security guard.
当保安太可惜了
My dad has left
我爸已经离开
that department store.
那家百货公司
He comes to a security company,
到一家保安公司
and becomes the director.
当主任了
In short,
总之
the dust has finally settled.
现在终于尘埃落定了
Everybody now
大家现在
can prepare for the debate without any burden.
可以轻装上阵了
Let's start preparing for the debate.
我们开始准备辩题吧
Hello
孩儿们
Look
看看撒老师
what I brought you.
给你们带什么来了
Are you exhausted?
都累坏了吧
Let's replenish our energy.
来 咱们充个电
And then let's continue to practice.
然后接着操练
Come on.
来
Thank you, Hao.
谢谢小好姐
That means
就是说
you can tell everyone about
你把你刚才省略掉的
the ones you omitted just now.
那些再给大家说一说
Let's talk again.
让大家再聊一聊
OK.
好
Excuse me.
打扰了
Tao Hao
陶好
Oh?
喔
Hao,
小好啊
what is the situation?
这是什么情况呀
Tell us something about it.
给我们介绍一下吧
Senior,
学长
I have a boyfriend.
我有男朋友了
What does it matter to me?
你有男朋友关我什么事
You are talking about this.
你说这个
These flowers are that
这个是学校办公室
the school office teacher doesn't want them.
老师不要了
I think about taking them back for decoration.
我想着拿它回去做装饰
Oh.
哦
This is senior Ma Nan,
这个是学生会的
who belongs to the student union.
马楠学长
We've bought shoes together.
咱俩不是一块买过鞋吗
Men may meet but mountains never.
人生何处不相逢
Senior, you come here today...
那学长你今天来是
Oh,
哦
wait a minute.
你等一下
Take a look at this.
来 看看这个
Come on.
来
This is a portable foot soaking bucket.
便携式泡脚桶
It's easy to carry and ready to use.
携带方便 随时可用
It helps protect the liver and resist fatigue.
保肝脏 抗疲劳
The man can use it to keep fit.
男的用了强身健体
The woman can use it to maintain beauty.
女的用了美容养颜
You come to us to sell things.
你来我们这儿卖东西
Are you sure?
你确定吗
I'm doing this for
我这不是为了
collecting tuition.
凑重修费吗
Twenty yuan each.
二十块钱一个
Only for sale but not for free.
只卖不送
Let me give you a 15% discount.
给你们再打个八五折吧
Tell you
我跟你说
it's really suitable for you.
这东西可真适合你们
Young people who stay up all night while soaking wolfberry.
泡枸杞通宵的年轻人
How about it?
怎么样 要不要
This is not necessary.
这个就没有必要了吧
What do you think?
你们觉得呢
What if the other side says that
如果对方说
self-discipline needs to overcome
自律需要克服
the inherent inertia of human nature?
人性中本身的惰性
It is a difficult thing
是一件很难
with a low profit ratio.
收益比很低的事情
What to do?
怎么办
Then I say
那我说
the long-term benefits of self-discipline are higher.
自律的长期收益更高呢
The key is that
关键是人家不说
people can do without saying the profit ratio.
收益比也可以呀
For now,
就现在而言
the difficulty of overcoming laziness
克服懒惰的难度
is definitely higher than heteronomy.
绝对要高于他律
Heteronomy
那他律是一种
is a more effective method.
更行之有效的方法啊
Then we won't be affected.
那我们不受
Can we go around?
能不能绕过去
How to go around?
怎么绕啊
Heteronomy itself is a kind of laziness.
他律本身就是一种懒惰
What are you saying?
你说什么
Isn't heteronomy lazy?
他律不懒惰吗
It is the laziest.
他律最懒惰了
That makes sense.
说得有道理啊
Ah...
哎
If self-discipline
如果说自律
needs to overcome laziness,
需要克服懒惰的话
heteronomy
那他律本身
is a kind of laziness.
就是一种懒惰
It's definitely easier
被人推着走
to be pushed by someone
肯定要比自己
than to climb a mountain on your own.
爬上高山要更容易
So...
那
Heteronomy,
他律
to some extent,
在某种程度上
doesn't even have to choose the direction.
连方向都不用选择
Because others
因为他别人
have already chosen it for you.
已经给你选择好了
If you look at it this way,
照这么来看的话
for college students,
现在对于大学生而言
the more important
更重要的是
is laziness.
懒惰吗
We go around.
绕过去了
This point is too sharp.
这个点太犀利了
Have you played
你之前是不是
a debate before?
也打过辩论赛
Where is he?
人呢
Audience friends,
观众朋友们
good morning.
早上好
Welcome to today's
欢迎收看今天的
DUFE news program.
东财新闻节目
Today's main contents are as follows.
今天的主要内容有
Mr. Li arrived at the branch campus
李主任抵达分校区
for an official friendly visit
对同学们
to the students.
进行正式友好访问
The 26th meeting of the student union
学生会第二十六次会议
was held in dormitory 113.
在宿舍一一三召开
Dormitory 343 and 502
宿舍三四三和五零二
are conducting joint military exercises.
正在进行联合军事演习
The competition between the Dongzhou University of Finance and Economics
原东财大
and the Western University of Science and Technology
和西科大
debate teams
辩论校队的比赛
will kick off today.
将于今天拉开帷幕
Please see the detailed report below.
下面请看详细报道
Sit down.
坐吧
I'll sit here.
我坐这儿
You sit here.
你坐这儿
Welcome to today's
欢迎大家来到今天的
debate.
迎新辩论赛
Let's first get to know
让我们先来认识一下
the positive side.
今天的正方
Their view is that
他们的观点是大学生活
self-discipline is more important in college life.
自律更重要
Let's welcome them.
让我们欢迎他们
And the opposite side
而他们挑战的反方
is made up of
则是由去年在全国赛中
the brilliant star of national competition last year.
大放异彩的校队新星
Yin Nan serves as the second debater.
殷楠担任二辩
Dongzhou star debater,
东州市明星辩手
Liu Yanze is the captain.
刘彦泽担任队长
They are the opposing side.
他们是今天的反方
Their view is that
他们的观点是
heteronomy is more important in college life.
大学生活 他律更重要
And let's
也让我们
give them applause.
把掌声送给他们
Why doesn't she introduce us?
不 为什么不介绍咱们啊
Do you have any good grades
你大学以后有什么成绩
in college?
是拿得出手的吗
They are professor Chen Ji,
他们是陈杰教授
professor Min Ruiwu,
闵瑞伍教授
professor Guo Xinggang,
郭星刚教授
and professor Zhao Hongxia.
赵红霞教授
Let's welcome them.
让我们欢迎他们
At the same time,
同时本次比赛
students from Dongzhou City
由东州市
Debate League
辩论联盟的同学们
serve as technical judges in this competition.
出任技术裁判
Let's also
也让我们把
give them applause.
掌声送给他们
Now I declare that
现在我宣布
the debate officially starts.
比赛正式开始
Let's enter the argument session of both sides.
下面进入双方立论环节
Three minutes for each side.
每方时间三分钟
In the meantime, the other side has the right to question.
其间对方有权提出检证
The time is one and a half minutes.
时间为一分半
Let's start with
下面我们首先
the positive side.
有请正方开宗明义
Please
有请
Thank you.
谢谢主席
Hello, everyone.
大家好
Our view today is
今天我方的观点是
self-discipline is more important in college life.
大学生活 自律更重要
How should we
我们应该怎么
understand this sentence?
理解这句话呢
College life is a special stage,
大学生活就是从校园
from the campus to the society.
到社会过渡的特殊阶段
This is also a critical period
也是我们培养
for us
自身能力的
to cultivate our own capabilities.
关键时期
Therefore, the so-called importance
因此所谓的重要性
will also be different
也会因为
due to the particularity
这个阶段的特殊
of this stage.
而有所不同
The definition is so biased.
定义这么偏
This is to seduce us to raise objections
这是勾引我们提出异议
to launch the first battlefield.
展开第一个战场吗
Question us.
来质疑我们呀
Come on.
来呀
Yin Nan
殷楠
Come on!
接招啊
Xiaoyu
小鱼
I support you.
我挺你
You're
果然是
my good friend.
心有灵犀的好姐妹
Then what is more important?
那什么是更重要呢
We believe that
我方认为
because the ability to focus on training
因为人生的不同阶段
is different
所需专注
at different stages of life,
培养的能力不同
what
因此在现阶段中
needs more energy
什么需要
to learn and cultivate
我们付出更多的精力
at this stage
去学习培养
is more important.
什么也就更为重要
Compared with heteronomy,
相比起他律
self-discipline is obviously
自律显然是
the shortcoming
大多数大学生
of most college students.
的短板所在
Therefore,
因此
This point...
这个点
Let's ask the second debater of the opposing side
下面有请反方二辩
to raise a question about this.
对其提出质询
The time is one and a half minutes.
时间为一分半钟
I want to confirm it.
确认一下
Which one do you think
您认为何者需要
requires more time and effort
付出更多时间精力
is more important, right?
何者就更重要 对吗
It's okay to understand in this way.
这样理解也可以
Do you need to spend a lot of time and energy
挣钱要不要
to make money?
付出很多时间精力呢
Generally speaking, yes.
一般来说是的
Breathing usually doesn't require
那呼吸一般不需要付出
a lot of time and energy.
很多时间精力
According to your logic,
按照您的逻辑
money is more important than breathing. Right?
钱比呼吸重要 对吗
It's absurd.
归谬了啊
My fellow debater,
对方辩友
this is an inappropriate comparison.
您这是比较不当
Breathing usually doesn't require
呼吸不需要
a lot of time and energy.
您付出时间精力
But self-discipline needs to
但自律却是
be learned and cultivated.
需要学习培养的
This is an inappropriate comparison.
您这是缺失性比较
What about inappropriate comparison?
缺失性比较又怎么样呢
One can be missed and the other can't be missed.
一个可以缺 一个不能缺
Doesn't it show
重要性这不就
the importance?
比出来了吗
This is not the point.
重点不是缺不缺
What we have been stressing is that
我方一直在强调的是
self-discipline requires learning.
自律是需要学习成本的
OK, let's say another example.
好 那再比如说
I can't make up.
我不会化妆
But I can eat.
可我会吃饭啊
So for me,
所以对我来说
makeup that needs to be learned
需要学习的化妆
is more important
比不用学习的
than eating that doesn't need to learn.
吃饭重要对吗
Don't you need to learn to eat?
吃饭不用学习吗
Do you use chopsticks
您是一出生就会用筷子
when you are born
还是一落地
or use knives and forks?
就会使刀叉呢
When I was a child, my parents chased me
小时候爸妈还追着
to tell me to eat.
叫我好好吃饭呢
So whether it is important or not,
所以重不重要
we have to consider the urgency.
还得考虑紧迫性
For example,
比如说现在
if I'm going on a date now,
如果我要去约会
makeup is more important.
那当然是化妆更重要
So, urgency
所以 所以紧迫性
equals importance, right?
等于重要性了
Skip the standard.
跳标准了
Our judgment criteria are very comprehensive.
我方的判断标准很综合
Of course, the urgency
当然紧迫性
is taken into account.
也是需要考虑在内的
Marriage is
婚姻对我来说
not very urgent for me.
就不是很紧迫
So in my life,
所以在我的人生当中
is marriage not important?
婚姻是不重要的吗
This...
这个
She's stuck.
卡壳了 死殷楠
Solving urgent problems
解决紧迫性问题
and the urgency of problems
和问题的紧迫性
are two different things.
是两回事儿
Let me summarize.
我结一下
The standard of positive side
今天对方辩友的标准
jumps from time and effort
从付出时间精力
to urgency.
跳到紧迫性
It's always unconvincing.
始终不具备说服力
She also fails to justify herself.
也未能自圆其说
And our standard is
而我方的标准为
between self-discipline and heteronomy,
自律和他律
what can help us grow
更能够帮助我们
is more important.
成长的就更重要
Thank you.
谢谢
Yin Nan's operation
殷楠的操作
disintegrates the opponent's standards.
把对方标准瓦解掉了
Very good.
很好
OK.
好
Next,
那么接下来
I'll continue to expound our view.
继续阐述我方观点
University
大学是我们
is our first step
迈向成年生活的
towards adult life.
第一步
It is also the first time
也是第一次
to learn...
我们必须学会
Their team looks quite strong.
他们队看着还挺强的
Can Nan Bei control the situation?
南北能掌控得住吗
What do you mean?
什 什么意思
It means
那意思刚刚那一部分
Nan Bei lost that part.
南北他们队输了
Do you really not understand?
你是真的听不懂吗
Therefore, we firmly believe that
因此我方坚定地认为
self-discipline is more important in college life.
大学生活自律更重要
Thank you.
谢谢
Let's welcome the first debater of opposing side to argue.
下面有请反方一辩立论
Hello, everyone.
大家好
Our view is very simple.
我方今天的观点很简单
Whether it is self-discipline or heteronomy,
无论是自律还是他律
what can effectively help us
能够有效帮助
grow
我们成长的
is the most important.
才是最重要的
The other side's argument consists of three arguments.
对方立论一共三个论点
Adults need to be more self-discipline.
成年人更需要自律
The standard of self-discipline is higher than that of heteronomy.
自律的标准高于他律
So it is more conducive to growth.
所以更有利于成长
And the cost of losing self-discipline
以及 失去自律的代价
is more serious.
更加严重
It's clear.
清晰明了
It depends on whether you can defend it or not.
就看你们守不守得住了
We lost a section in argument.
立论上输了一节
Hope Nan Bei's cross-examination
希望接下来南北的盘问
can save a little bit of the situation.
能挽回一点颓势吧
Let's go to the cross-examination session.
下面进入盘问环节
First of all, please ask the second debater
首先有请正方二辩
to cross-examine
对反方一三四辩
the opposing side.
进行盘问
Please.
有请
It is emphasized in your argument that
您方立论中强调
the effect of self-discipline
自律的效果
is not as good as heteronomy. Right?
不如他律对吗
The fourth debater
四辩
Yes.
是的
Ancient slaves
古代的奴隶
relied on heteronomy,
依靠的是他律
and yeomen relied on self-discipline.
自耕农依靠的是自律
Which effect is better?
请问哪个效果更好呢
The third debater
三辩
Yeoman.
自耕农
But the restraint of slaves
但约束奴隶的
cannot be regarded as heteronomy.
不能算他律
It is compulsory.
那是被强制的
OK. So
好 所以被
what is forced is not heteronomy,
强制的不算是他律
but what is willing
自己心甘情愿的
is heteronomy.
才叫他律
Shouldn't this be called self-discipline?
这不就应该叫自律吗
Go back to your argument.
回到您方的立论
What do you think is the biggest resistance
您方认为自律面临
to self-discipline?
最大的阻力是什么
The fourth debater
四辩
Self-discipline needs to overcome
自律需要克服
a lot of resistance.
非常多的阻力
For example, we are born to be lazy.
比如我们的天性爱偷懒
No.
不行
Nan Bei can't
南北对刘彦泽
form an effective attack
完全无法形成
on Liu Yanze.
有效进攻
Get around him.
绕开他
But relying on others
可是依靠别人
to manage your heteronomy
来管理自己的他律
is lazy itself. Am I right?
本身不也是一种偷懒吗
The first debater
一辩
Yes.
是的
But what's wrong with being lazy?
但是偷懒有什么问题呢
From the telegraph, telephone to the Internet,
从电报 电话到互联网
from cars and ships
从汽车 轮船到
to airplanes and high-speed rail,
飞机 高铁
learning to be lazy correctly
学会正确地偷懒
is simply
简直就是
the first productive force that promotes progress.
推动进步的第一生产力
Why does the first productive force
为什么作为第一生产力
become a resistance
在您方就变成了
on your side?
是阻力了呢
The third debater
三辩
This issue is not related to today's debate.
这个问题与今天的辩论
Serial sophistry.
连环诡辩
No logic is normal.
没有一个逻辑是正常的
The other side didn't react.
对方就没反应过来吧
Over-reliance on heteronomy
过度依赖他律
cannot develop the habit of self-discipline.
无法养成自律的习惯
What shall we do?
怎么办呢
When you are riding a bike,
你在骑单车的时候
your father has been holding you.
你爸一直扶着你
You can never learn well. Am I right?
你是不是就一直学不会
The fourth debater
四辩
If my dad doesn't hold me,
如果我爸不扶着我
I may not even dare to step onto the bike.
我可能都不敢跨上去
This is what we emphasize.
这就是我方强调的
Heteronomy is the premise and foundation
他律是自律的
of self-discipline.
前提和基础
In this case,
在这个案例中
heteronomy is the father of self-discipline.
他律是自律的爹
Will we say
我们会说
father is more important than son?
父亲比儿子更重要吗
The first debater
一辩
No.
不会
But this has nothing to do with
但这跟我们今天
our debate.
的辩题没有任何
If we say heteronomy
那就算是他律
is the father of self-discipline,
是自律他爹
why is heteronomy
那他律为什么
more important?
就更重要呢
It seems to
场面上
save the competition.
勉强挽回一局
If we can survive
如果接下来的盘问
the next cross-examination,
我们能够扛下来
the situation will be balanced.
局势就均衡了
The fourth debater
请教四辩
Do you think
您方认为对于
for adults
成年人来说
self-discipline is more important than heteronomy?
自律比他律更重要是吗
Yes.
是的
But
但是
we think...
我们认为 好的
Then since heteronomy
那既然他律
is not so important,
没有那么重要
why is the law
那为什么法律对成年人
stricter on adults
比对未成年人
than on minors?
要求更严格呢
The third debater
三辩
Because many of us
因为我们很多大学时候
didn't form the good habit
都没有养成
of self-discipline in college.
自律的好习惯
For example, don't interrupt others' speeches
比如不要随意
at will.
打断别人的发言
The kindergarten teacher
这个幼儿园老师
should have taught it.
应该也教过吧
The interrogator can interrupt.
质询方可以打断
This is my right
是比赛规则
given by the rules of the debate.
赋予我的权利
My fellow debater
对方辩友对
lacks respect for heteronomy.
他律的不尊重
This may be
也许正是您方
the crux of your point of view.
观点的症结所在
With the so-called
倒是拿着所谓
self-discipline at kindergarten level,
幼儿园级别的自律
it's self-empowerment actually.
在这里自我赋权
You are talking to yourself and singing your own praises.
自说自话 自鸣得意
It seems a little childish.
显得有些小孩子气
You point out that
您方指出
standard of self-discipline
自律的标准
is higher than heteronomy. Right?
要高于他律对吗
The third debater
三辩
If it's the same thing, yes.
在同一件事情上是这样
Why? The first debater
为什么呢 一辩
Because heteronomy is often the bottom line.
因为他律往往是底线
For example, the school rules
比如校规
stipulate that I go to class at eight o'clock.
规定我八点上课
This is heteronomy.
这是他律
But the rules I give myself
可是我给自己的规定
is half past eight.
是八点半上课
Then how can I
那我怎么还有脸
call it self-discipline?
自称自律呢
This is not self-discipline.
这是不自律
Is there no self-discipline
没有自律
lower than heteronomy?
低于他律的情况吗
The fourth debater
四辩
No.
没有
For example, the criminal example
比如您刚才
you just cited.
举的罪犯的例子
Their self-demand
他们的自我要求
is lower than the law.
比法律还低
It can't be called self-discipline, right?
那就不能叫自律了 对吧
If my parents ask
如果我的父母要求
me to take the first place in my class,
我一定要考全班第一
but I want to
但我对自己的要求
be in the top ten.
是进前十名就好
Is it the standard of self-discipline
是不是自律的标准
lower than heteronomy? The third debater
就低于了他律呢 三辩
Parents have great ambitions for their child.
一定要求孩子人中龙凤
It is
本身就是
unreasonable heteronomy.
不合理的他律嘛
So
所以
your argument
所以您方论证的
is that reasonable self-discipline
是合理的自律
is more important than
比不合理的他律
unreasonable heteronomy.
更重要了
Can we
那我方是不是
also argue that
也可以论证
reasonable heteronomy
合理的他律
is more important than
比不合理的自律
unreasonable self-discipline?
更重要呢
She knows that Xiaoyu is used to fighting back.
她知道小鱼习惯反击
She's luring Xiaoyu to foul.
她在引诱小鱼犯规
So does your arguments
所以您方的立论定义中
also include
也包含了
unreasonable heteronomy?
不合理的他律吗
Do you have to
难道对那些
accept
严以待人的所谓他律
all the so-called heteronomy that treats others strictly?
您方也要照单全收吗
Attention please.
请注意
The side being questioned shall not ask.
被质询方不得反问
Thank you.
谢谢
I'm so stupid.
我真是太蠢了
I lost the technical points.
居然丢了技术分
Yin Nan is too sinister.
殷楠也太阴险了吧
Two main arguments
两条主要论点
are breached.
都折进去了
Not good.
不妙啊
This round
本轮
is ours.
拿下
If Nan Bei loses
如果下一轮
in the next round of defense,
南北的攻辩继续输掉
I am afraid there is really no chance.
恐怕就真没机会了
Don't worry.
小傻子 别着急啊